{
  "reference_number": "7651",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The government should only commit to emissions intensity targets. The countries with the largest emissions in the Paris Agreement\n have not have not capped total emissions. To cap in once country and not another will result in the manufacture and the means of\n production relocating."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Emissions intensity targets only."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Global carbon trading schemes implemented to date have not reduced emissions and have only created an environment for traders\n and speculators to personally gain from tax payers and consumers."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I do not support the implementation of targets. It is becoming increasingly likely that CO2 is not driving climate change as such we\n\n should be able to change our position as the science matures. Also if the social impact of the legislation is too great there should be\n an option to roll it back."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Commitments to emissions intensity is the only fair position given the global context."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": "The government of the day should have the option to review any of the budgets."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The government of the day should have the option to review any of the budgets."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "These should be minimum considerations. They should also be objective, published with supporting documentation in the public\ndomain and contestable."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "There must be a costed and independently reviewed implementation plan. Targets should not be set without a realistic plan for\ndelivery being agreed in the public domain."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "There are numerous issues issues. Please refer to the supplementary information provided with this submission via email."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I oppose any mechanism that makes the climate commission independent of government. This is not democratic and the\ncommission should only have an advisory role in all aspects. The government should not be obliged in any form other than public\n\npressure to act on the advice provided."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "The commission should only have advisory capacity. Anything over and above this is anti-democratic."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes there are numerous considerations for any policy position and these all need to be fully evaluated to avoid negative outcomes."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Climate change is a natural phenomenon that we can not stop or stabilize as such adaptation is a natural part of life since the\n\nbeginning of time. It should be our primary and only concern."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Partially agree. The creation of an adaptation plan is advised but this must be subject to review and based on science that is\n\nsupported by empirical evidence. The actions should also be regularly reviewed as new information comes to light. Emphasis on\nchoice and personal responsibility as opposed to regulation should be the primary mechanism of the plan."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "This is an over reach of government."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Supplementary information attached."
    }
  ]
}
